Finding aid for the Henry A. Waxman papers LSC.2261
UCLA Library Special Collections
Henry A. Waxman papers
1971-2014
UCLA Library Special Collections
Waxman, Henry A.
LSC.2261
278 linear feet (278 cartons)
8.8 linear feet (2 unprocessed boxes, 1 unprocessed half-box, 7 unprocessed cartons, 2 unprocessed flat boxes)
Henry A. Waxman served as a lawyer in private practice and as a member of the California State Assembly from 1969 until 1974. In 1974 he was elected as Congressman for the California Twenty-fourth district, and served in Congress from 1975 to 2015. During his time in the US House of Representatives, Waxman participated in creating and passing legislation pertaining to a number of issues ranging from the environment and health care to government reform. He retired from the US House of Representatives in 2015. The collection consists of committee files and personal office files related to Waxman's tenure in Congress, and a small number of awards.
Conditions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Portions of this collection (boxes 91, 100, 101, 104, 112, 113, 124, 125, 126, 127, 128, 129, 130, 132, 133, 134, 188, 189, 195, 196, 197, 198, 199, 216, 217, 218, 229, 231, 232, 275 and 276) are closed until the year 2025. Unprocessed Box 9 is restricted.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL AND AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: This collection contains processed digital and audiovisual materials. All requests to access digital materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Henry A. Waxman, 2014.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9976205033606533
Biography/History
Henry Arnold Waxman was born on September 12, 1939, in the City of Los Angeles. He earned a B.A. (1961) and J.D. (1964) from the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA). Waxman served as a lawyer in private practice and as a member of the California State Assembly from 1969 until 1974. In 1974 he was elected as Congressman for the California Twenty-fourth district, and served in Congress from 1975 to 2015. During his time in Congress, Waxman served as the chair of the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform (during the One Hundred Tenth Congress, 2007-2009) and Chair of the House Energy and Commerce Committee (during the One Hundred Eleventh Congress, 2009-2011). Waxman is known for his support and involvement in the reduction of air pollution, tobacco industry reforms, expanding Medicaid coverage, and encouraging Congress to provide improved care, treatment, and support to Americans with HIV/AIDS, among his other accomplishments. During his career, Waxman earned a reputation as a productive and successful lawmaker.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of materials related to the career of Congressman Henry A. Waxman. The bulk of the collection documents Waxman's committee work while serving for the United States House of Representatives. Included are notes, research, printed copies of Congressional acts, correspondence, videos, and other records related to public and social issues such as the Clean Air Act and other environmental issues; health reform issues such as tobacco, Medicaid, nursing homes, and steroids; the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform; the Committee on Energy and Commerce; and other matters. Additionally included are press releases, personal calendars and a small number of awards.
Organization and Arrangement
Collection has been organized into the following series:
Series 1. Committee Files
Series 2. Personal Office Files
Legislators -- United States -- Archives; Politicians -- United States -- California -- Archives.; Waxman, Henry A. -- Archives
- Committee Files, (1971-2014, bulk 1995-2010); 1995-2010; (Boxes 1-233)
  Scope and Content
  This series consists of materials related to committee work of the United States House of Representatives in which Congressman Waxman participated in during his tenure as a Representative. Included are notes, research, printed copies of Congressional acts, transcripts, correspondence, and other records related to the Clean Air Act and other environmental issues; health reform issues such as tobacco, Medicaid, nursing homes, and steroids; the Committee on Oversight and Government Reform; the Committee on Energy and Commerce; and other matters.
  Restrictions on Access
  Box numbers 91, 100, 101, 104, 112, 113, 124 - 130, 132 133,134, 188, 189, 195, 196, 197, 198, 199, 216, 217, 218, 229, 231, and 232 are closed until the year 2025.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials, please notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection will require assessment and possible digitization for safe access. To review these audiovisual materials, you must notify the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk in advance of your visit.
  - ACES, undated (Box 87)
    Scope and Contents note
    Carbon market; Oversight, factsheet, notes; Renewable Energy Standards (RES); Municipal Solid Waste (MSW) and waste-to-energy; Transmission/energy grid.
  - ACES, 2004 (Box 100)
    RESTRICTED: This box is closed until the year 2025.
    RESTRICTED: This box is closed until the year 2025. ACES - post passage; Bill summaries, R debate kit on ACES (6/04); Draft text - manager's amendment & floor; Revisions in progress; permitting; Markup & Democrat amendments; Draft text - post markup; Building codes drafts & comments; Draft text - coal & offsets; Draft text - changes to DD for markup text & comments on DD; Stakeholder comments; Draft text - energy efficiency; ACES - development of discussion draft; ACES committee markup support materials.
  - Affordable Care Act Back Room Deals Investigation, undated (Box 196)
  - Affordable Care Act Back Room Deals Investigation, undated (Box 197)
  - Affordable Care Act Back Room Deals Investigation, undated (Box 198)
  - Affordable Care Act Back Room Deals Investigation, undated (Box 199)
  - BHP Billiton investigation, undated (Box 88)
    BHP Billiton investigation; BHP investigation; Interviews; Copies of exhibits; Interview transcripts ? Amy Zimpfer, Deborah Jordan; FERC Southern Power case; 9th Circuit opinion on Enron.
  - Bicameral Task Force, undated (Box 216)
    Climate Hearing Requests; Other Climate/Enviro Topics.
    RESTRICTED: This box is closed until the year 2025. Climate Hearing Requests; Other Climate/Enviro Topics.
  - BP oil spill, 2009, 2011 (Box 92)
    Blowout Prevention Act drafts, hearings, amendments, talking points; USEC pensions; HR 4082 of 2009; Clean Air Act; Boiler & utility MACTs; TRAIN Act; EPA GHG Regulations; Upton bill hearing, Upton repeal bill; 3/8/04 climate science hearing; Transmission; MISO cost allocation; 10/13/11 transmission hearing; FERC IDOE delegation; RTO swaps.
  - BPA and Pedernales, undated (Box 82)
    BPA/CERH; Meeting notes with BPA scientists, NIEHS, CERHR; EPA studies, proposed and final rules; Pedernales Electric Cooperative; Lawsuit depositions; Co-op misc.
  - Bush Administration Oversight, 1995 (Box 99)
    Enron; Industry Contributions report; Letters; Fact Sheets, memos; EPA - shop towels; Press; IG report; Gravel mining / Solis; Key secrecy documents; Congressional access to information; 9-11 Commission; 7-member census & Medicare costs materials; CAO litigation; PACA legislative exemptions; NRDC FOIA examples; Administration stonewalling of information requests; Preemption project; Sen. Murray / Rep. Waxman - asbestos; Regulation rollback - 1995 materials; Paducah, ICY gaseous diffusion & Qui Tam case.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
    CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials, please notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - CA Energy Crisis/Deregulation, undated (Box 175)
    H Con. Res. 328; HR 3464 & Report; HR 2773.
  - California waiver, undated (Box 90)
    EPA denial ? correspondence and public documents; Notes; Transcripts; ?Redacted? documents.
  - Campaign Finance Files, undated (Box 114)
    DNC scheduling documents, requests, correspondence; Briefing/reception planning documents; DNC finance reports & scanned checks; Senate Committee on Government Affairs Special Investigation depositions.
  - Campaign Finance Files, undated (Box 115)
    Investigation witness files; Wayne Skinner - Eric Sullivan.
  - Campaign Finance Files, undated (Box 116)
    Investigation witness files; Roberta Ma-Mack McLarty.
  - Campaign Finance Investigation Files, undated (Box 105)
    Staff interim reports; Riady & Huang Exs. 1-60; Obstruction Exs. 1-15; Chpt. 3 Contribution Review Exs. 1-150; Chpt. 3 Contribution Review Exs. 151-300; Chpt. 3 Contribution Review Exs. 301-368; Trie Exhibits 1-155; Castro Exhibits 1-24; FEC Exhibits -26.
  - Campaign Finance Investigation Files, undated (Box 106)
    Investigative reports/depositions; Hudson Casino depositions.
  - Campaign Finance Work Product, undated (Box 120)
    Green, Earnest Deposition Materials; Waxman-Burton Correspondence re: Green Deposition; Chung, Johnny Materials; Kerry-Chung; Trie, Charlie and PLET Documents; Hsia, Maria Materials; Bank of China Materials; Lennon, Fred Materials; Republican Fundraising Materials; Chiang, Charlie Materials.
  - Campaign Finance Work Product, undated (Box 121)
    Sioeng & Elintiarta Documents; Wang, David Documents; Wang, Chi Documents; Xiong Depositions; Sioeng, Ted Correspondence; Sioeng, Ted Documents; Deposition Summaries/Notes; Immunity Materials.
  - Carbon Market, undated (Box 194)
    Nursing Home Statistics; Veteran Data; CMS Senior Analysis.
  - Clean Air Act Files, 1990s (Box 161)
    Inspection and Maintenance; Reform.
  - Clean Air Act Files (2000-2005) (Box 98)
    NSR Oversight 2002; HAW letters; Press; EPA Air Oversight; GAO air toxics program study (2003); Latham white paper (3/04); Risk-based MACT letters & background; Correspondence on O3 rule NAAQS (3/08); CSI hearing (7-8-03); Letters; Transcript; EPA elevation - 108th (2003); Mercury - International negotiations & 7 - member letter; Mercury MACT - post-proposal; letters; chronology; EPA multi-pollutant analyses; EPA court losses; Letters, press.
  - Clean Air Standards Files, 1997 (Box 178)
    HAW Roll Call Article; LA Air Toxics Report; HAW Clean Air Op-Ed.
  - Clean Air Standards Files, 1997 (Box 185)
    HAW/APHA Op Ed; EWG Clean Air Reports; CASAC Letters.
  - Clean Air Standards Files, 1997 (Box 187)
    EPA?s correspondence w/Burton; GM Letter; SBA/EPA correspondence.
  - Climate, undated (Box 168)
    Energy, Toxics, Clear skies.
  - Climate Change, 1990s-2000 (Box 166)
  - Climate Change Task Force, 1999, 2000, 2006, 2007 (Box 188)
    RESTRICTED: This box is closed until the year 2025. Climate Change task force; Pro task sports forum; Summaries of Oversight Committee (special investigations division reports) 1999 Oil refinery Leaks Report; 2000 Voting Investigation; Jan 2006 Part D Drug Briefing; Floyd Landis USADA Steroid Case; Documents April 2007.
  - Climate Files (not ACES):, 1992 (Box 102)
    Climate principles; HR 1590 Safe Climate Act; Comments on HR 1590; HAW climate materials 1992; Schedule & jurisdiction; Energy bill drafts - late conferences.
  - Climate Oversight 2006-2008 (Box 97)
    Financing coal plants; RUS financing, background, RUS & Farm Bill, press; Sunflower press & HAW letter, background; coal plant financing; Stationary source GHG regulation; NSR routine maintenance rule 2008; Carbon capture bill; Hearing on power plant approval; Transcripts, questions, memo, HAW statement; Coal plant permitting letters & press; Records for White Pine, Desert Rock, Deseret; Deseret EPA document production; EPA's denial for California waiver petition - correspondence and public documents; Oversight on CA waiver question; Press, waiver correspondence; Johnson waiver denial letter; CA waiver request; CA motor vehicle GHG emissions law; HAW talking points & letter; support for waiver; Final letter & press (9/06); Government Reform Committee - hearing on climate change; Press, questions, HAW statement, hearing request; Bush Administration & California; Barton & Hockey Stick - letter, hearing.
  - Climate/CWA/CEQ, 2007 (Box 85)
    Clean Water Act; Investigation, correspondence, doc. Request and review; Politicization of climate science; Political interference; 3/19/07 hearing & transcript; CEQ; Press; CEQ report documents.
  - Climate/Ozone, 2004, 2007 (Box 83)
    Co-op misc.; Ozone/climate; Velders paper, 5/23/07 Montreal Protocol hearing, 6/4/07 Drusilla briefing; Montreal Protocol; Primatene mist, methyl bromide bill; Methyl bromide; Hearings (06/03, 7/21/04); HCFC legislation; Global Climate and Ozone Layer Protection Act of 2007; USA refrigerant management.
  - Climate/Ozone, 2007-2008 (Box 84)
    Climate; Political interference hearing ? 1/30/07; GAP climate report, March 2007; Ozone; Ozone NAAQs, May 2008 hearings, subpoenas, executive privilege claims; NAS ozone report ? 4/22/08; Jason Burnett (EPA) deposition.
  - Columbia/drugs, 1998, 2000 (Box 214)
    Russian spying ? 2000; Judge Norma Holloway Johnson; Waco correspondence; Campaign Finance Investigations; Democratic National Committee; Cheryl Mills; John Huang & Charlie Trie, improper fundraising; Johnny Chung & related correspondence; Chung deposition; 106th Congress subpoena; Charles Parrish, US Consulate in Beijing visa fraud; DeLay investigations; Correspondence from agencies; Campaign finance report investigations of costs; GAO investigation of costs; DOJ ? cost of DOJ/FBI investigation; Hearings; FEC subcommittee hearing ? March 5, 1998; Hearing notices, statements, questions, other testimony, background; Bingaman hearing ? February 25, 1998; Statistics, deposition summaries
  - Committee on Energy and Commerce Files, 2009 (Box 67)
    Bayer crop science; explosion in WV Institute.
  - Committee on Energy and Commerce Files, 2009 (Box 68)
    Peanut Corporation recall; hearing with Stewart Parnell & FDA; March 2009.
  - Committee on Energy and Commerce Files, 2009 (Box 69)
    Work files; Crib safety.
  - Committee on Energy and Commerce Files, 2009 (Box 70)
    Hearing with Stewart Parnell & FDA.
  - Committee on Energy and Commerce Files, 2009 (Box 71)
    Anthem Blue Cross; 2010 Premium rate increases; pre-existing conditions & maternity coverage; medicine advantage report (2009); Phillip Morris child labor.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2007 July (Box 33)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2007 July-Dec (Box 34)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2007 Aug (Box 35)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2007 Sept (Box 36)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2007 Oct (Box 37)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2007 Nov - Dec (Box 38)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2008 Jan - Feb (Box 40)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2008 March - April (Box 41)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2008 May (Box 42)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2008 June - July (Box 43)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2008 Aug - Sept (Box 44)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Chronological Files, 2008 Nov - Dec (Box 45)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 1995-1996 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 1996-1999 (Box 2)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 1996-2000 (Box 3)
    Other Waxman letters (June-December 1999); Waxman to Burton letters (1998-2000); letters to HAW (1999-2000); SID letters (1999-2000); Campaign Finance letters (1999-2000); Drug Request letters and forms; Environment letters; Tobacco letters.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 1996-2000 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 1996-2004 (Box 5)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 1997 (Box 6)
    Letters to Waxman from Burton; letters to Burton from Waxman; Human Resources and Interrelations subcommittee; National Economic Growth, Natural Resources, and Regulatory affairs; incoming mail (July-August 1997).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 1997 (Box 7)
    Briefing book; incoming correspondence (April 1997); incoming correspondence (May 1997); incoming correspondence (September-October 1997); incoming correspondence (November-December 1997).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 1997 April-2001 Oct (Box 48)
    Burton's Subpoenas; Enron.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 2000-2003 (Box 24)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 2003 (Box 25)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, 2003 (Box 26)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, undated (Box 28)
    Hatch Act; Mad Cow; Heroin Crisis.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, undated (Box 29)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Correspondence, undated (Box 31)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 1987, 2001 (Box 208)
    HAW Miscellaneous Letters; Burton: 2001 Bush Letters; HAW letter: Burton; OSE Gift Bill; Postal Bill; GR Budget; HAW Floor Folder: December 10, 1987; Homeland Security Legislation.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 1998 (Box 9)
    Depositions and correspondence (1998).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 1998 Mar (Box 119)
    Campaign Finance Investigation - FEC Hearings; Exhibits for FEC hearings, March 1998.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 1998-1999 (Box 10)
    Subpoena (1998-1999).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 1998-2001 (Box 8)
    Correspondence on Campaign Finance and Enron Taskforce (1998- 2001).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 1999 (Box 11)
    National Security Criminal Justice Subcommittee correspondence (1999).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 1999 (Box 12)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 1999 (Box 13)
    Postal Service Subcommittee; National Economic Growth, Natural Resources & Regulatory Affairs Subcommittee; A-Z correspondence; Census Subcommittee; Civil Service Subcommittee; Subcommittee on Criminal Justice, Drug Policy, Human Resources; Roll Call 1; District of Columbia Subcommittee; Roll Call 2; Full Committee; Roll Call 3; Government Management Subcommittee; letters to Burton from Waxman; letters from Waxman to Burton; Dear Colleague; Committee Democrats profile; Memos to Members.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 1999-2000 (Box 14)
    Bill correspondence (January 1999-December 2000).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2000 (Box 15)
    Correspondence; weekly schedule; Full Committee notices; Waxman press releases; Burton press releases; staff list for Hearings/Meetings; correspondence A-Z; Census Subcommittee; Government Management Subcommittee; Criminal Justice Subcommittee; National Economic Subcommittee; National Security Subcommittee; Postal Service Subcommittee; Style Manual; checklists for staff reports; Minority Rights manual.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2000-2005 (Box 16)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2000-2005 (Box 17)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2000-2005 (Box 18)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2000-2005 (Box 19)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2001 (Box 20)
    FEMA reports and other materials re: Gulf Coast states (February-June 2001).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2001-2003 (Box 46)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2001-2003 (Box 49)
    Politicization of Science.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2002 (Box 22)
    Technology Subcommittee; District of Columbia; Civil Service Subcommittee; Waxman press releases.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2002 (Box 23)
    Technology Subcommittee.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2002-2006 (Box 21)
    Investigation correspondence related to Executive life insurance (2002-2006).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2003-2004 (Box 50)
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2003-2006 (Box 51)
    Grant reports.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2004-2006 (Box 52)
    Trafficking of Persons.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2004-2007 (Box 54)
    Blackwater.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2005-2006 (Box 53)
    Central Personnel Data File.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2007 (Box 55)
    Investigations.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2007 (Box 137)
    Hearings, Investigations, and Bill Introductions (2007).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2007-2008 (Box 56)
    Interviews on Pre-War Intelligence.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 57)
    Blackwater Tax; Interrogation; IOTC.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 58)
    Clemens; AIG.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 59)
    AEM; Kosta Trebicka; DC Guns.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 60)
    Asset Deployment; Sons of Iraq; AEY Inc.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 61)
    Diplomatic security; private security contractor.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 62)
    Credit rating agencies; electrocutions; Fannie & Freddie; Iraqi Oil Contracts; military waivers; private security contractors.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 63)
    Pat Tillman; Investigation of Pat Tillman.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 64)
    AEY.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 65)
    AEY; Iraq weapons accountability.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 66)
    AEY; Major Carry Harrison; Ambassador Withers.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, 2008 (Box 138)
    Hearings, Investigations, and Bill Introductions (2008).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, undated (Box 72)
    Agricultural antibiotics; arsenic reports; CRS; census; voting; state assistance.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, undated (Box 73)
    Nursing homes; abuse reports; air toxics data archive; complaint reports; statements of deficiencies.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, undated (Box 118)
    Campaign Finance Investigation staff files; FEC evidence exhibits (RNC, GOPAC).
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, undated (Box 160)
    LNG; Ozone; Climate; Black Carbon.
  - Committee on Oversight and Government Reform Files, undated (Box 206)